The Buddha quite often warned people
about sensuality and sexuality.
But surely this was only for celebrate
monks and not for lay people, right?
There can't be anything inherently bad
in something as beautiful as physical
intimacy that you share with the person
you love.
>> Well, it wasn't for celebrate monks.
As if celebrate monks existed as a
given fact.
Celebrate monks started to exist
because of the need to give up
sensuality if you wanted to practice the
Buddhist teaching.
So, it's not like the Buddha these two
groups of people existed already.
And the Buddha created a different
message for each.
It is like different social classes or
something. No, it's he created an order
of celebrate monks
in order to practice his teaching.
In other words, those are the people who
actually accepted it fully. Everybody
else who wasn't actually a Buddhist in
in the full extent.
So, um
Uh yeah, you can say, you know, it's
beautiful and stuff, but the thing is
well, he he spoke of there is a
gratification in it
and in the world in general, but in
sensuality especially.
And he said if there wasn't any
gratification, then certainly nobody
would become attracted to things in the
world. So, there is a gratification.
So, there is a gratification.
Um but his whole teaching route
unlike the world
and most of the things you would find in
it, it doesn't stop there. It also tells
you there is a danger.
And then fortunately there's an escape
as well.
So, uh
while you recognize that okay, yes,
there is gratification and stuff,
you also have to recognize what is it
that comes with it.
And uh unless you're lying to yourself, you
uh unless you're lying to yourself, you
would see that
uh it also comes with uh fear,
with um um
concern,
with the eventual crash,
the eventual crash,
whether because, you know, circumstances
externally something like an accident
like a like a tragedy happened that
separated you from somebody that you
developed a connection with,
or uh that person abandons you
themselves out of their own choice.
And even if those two things don't
happen, the fact that you were
the fact that you were
physically and emotionally connected to
that person
means that you are already experiencing
the burden of those possibilities.
Like having something that you need to
protect is already painful
is already painful
even before something bad happens to it.
So, uh
uh
you have to recognize that
with that physical bond comes an
emotional bond as well.
And anybody who says otherwise is just
lying to themselves. Like you cannot not
emotionally care
and be concerned and and not be affected
by the loss of somebody that you have
had physical intimacy with or that you
expect to have physical intimacy with.
It's automatic that you will care about
that person and you will suffer if
something happens to them.
So, that is optional.
Like if you couldn't help it,
then sure, you could say like
uh
choose wisely like who you
get together with or whatever.
But the thing is you do have a choice
because as I said just before, there is
an escape which is
if that danger became sufficiently
apparent, you would lose desire for sexuality and
you would lose desire for sexuality and
sensuality.
And it's works the same as with
anything. Like if you were
uh in the habit of playing with vipers
your whole life since you were a kid.
It It might seem unthinkable to you
and that you would abstain from it or or
lose desire for it because it's
habitual. But at the same time,
But at the same time,
you recognize that it's just a a
principle of the mind
that the only way you can do something
is if you think that the benefit is
greater than the harm.
So, if that is flipped,
it doesn't matter what how many times
you did it before, that activity will
become impossible. There is nothing that
you can do.
Genuinely seeing more of a harm than a
benefit. Even if we even if it's a bad thing or
Even if we even if it's a bad thing or
or like self-harm or whatever,
you do it because you see for you either
you don't see the harm at all
or you perceive the harm as being lesser
than the benefit.
So, if you dwell on that harm,
then because it is actually there
in the same way as the gratification is
actually there, it's objectively there,
uh you will lose desire.
So, because it's it's on the same
universal footing, the fact that uh
certain things are agreeable, certain
things are beautiful, \ \,
it's on the same universal level
that to the extent that you have desire
for those things,
you have respond
that is like constantly having
repercussions. But in in in the sense of filling with
But in in in the sense of filling with
concern, filling you with
tension. So, So,
uh
you need to have like this
faith to some extent.
The same faith of a that an addict would
need to have
to realize that without his condition of
addiction, he would be better off.
Because if he isn't honest, he could
easily justify
uh himself into thinking that
you know, mental gymnastics himself into
thinking that
uh
it's kind of an inevitable.
It's not going to be that better anyway,
like it's going to be the same either
way, so it's not worth abandoning the
addiction. So, you need to see a problem with the
So, you need to see a problem with the
state where in which you're currently
in. And you need to have some amount of
And you need to have some amount of
faith that you can resolve it. And then
And then
pretty soon you will start to see that
actually at least part of the desire is is
at least part of the desire is is
optional.
Like, you know, it's it's it's you can
already start to see the results
of keeping the precepts, reflecting on
danger. You can start to see that
You can start to see that
it starts to go down, which
already shows you like
well, that that is uh at least partial
evidence that it is possible to overcome
it. And you would see like even if you
could never overcome it completely,
which is not true, but let's say
hypothetically, every grain of it you would have you
every grain of it you would have you
were worse off on account of it.
So, you'd still be better off by
decreasing it to the to the greatest
extent possible cuz
you would be decreasing it's like
decreasing the
amount of weight that you're carrying in
a backpack.
And again, it's just because you're used
to it. Because the only gratification
you know is the sensual one.
Uh
it feels to you like life starts there.
And everything else is kind of optional,
but this is the constant.
And that's actually not true. Like all
of this uh
the light in sensuality
is something that you could be without.
And yet like you can see how it
increased most likely. Like you can see how
most likely. Like you can see how
uh it wasn't as bad as it is now.
Or you could see how in the past uh it
was more, now it is less for whatever
reason. So, you can see that actually this is
So, you can see that actually this is
not constant and it is most certainly
being fed by my actions.
So, it would be
a sign as well of
overcoming sensuality
rightly or practicing towards it when
you when you dwell on the benefit that it
when you dwell on the benefit that it
gives you
even if you would stop right there.
Like you said, you overcome a little
grain of sensuality.
And even if you can't go any further for
whatever reason, because it's not
possible or you can't do it you're
factually better off than before.
>> Yeah. So, you you you don't uh
Like the Buddhist teaching is to abandon
all of it. Like the Buddhist teaching is
that craving is the root of suffering.
So, in line with the Buddhist teaching,
all sensuality
>> is unwholesome.
>> But it's still like uh
it's still up to you
in in the sense that
you won't be able to give it all up
overnight. But what matters is
that you don't change that perspective,
that you don't adopt the view
that some of the sensuality that you're
giving into is justified.
And then you will then at least you are
in the ballpark
of the Buddhist teaching and you will
most certainly be doing something to to
decrease the situation. Like you won't
be adding fuel to it cuz like I said
just now
if it is clear that the harm of
something outweighs the benefit
you can't possibly have a favorable
attitude towards it. It's just
mutually exclusive. You can't be trying
to get more of it.
So you might see yourself as like being
weak and
unable to to um
live up to your own ideals but your
ideals would be that sensuality clearly
you would see for yourself
is
like the Buddha said a charcoal pit.
That's a concrete statement of
the effect it has on your own mind. It's
not like a
um religious fearmongering or something.
Uh it is the the clear mechanistic mechanistic
influence
of how desiring essential pleasure
burns you internally.
And you could see that like
you could take an instance where you
don't have desire
for something.
And there is like some
hypothetical uh
uh
benefit in it to be had
but you don't find yourself having
desire for it.
And you could see like
and and let's say there is a
hypothetical benefit but then also there
is a very clear
harm that comes with it. So
like you know a very
uh
powerful drug that
kills you in a few years.
But, it will give you like the best
trips that you can imagine.
And you would see like, yes, that is a
factual benefit.
But, unless you were already addicted,
almost everyone would say no to that
because from where they're standing,
it's clear that even though there's a
gratification, the harm outweighs it
because you don't want to die in a few
years. Well,
Well,
for everybody who is
um
subjected to to sensual desire, they're
in the position of the addict who
because they it's painful to give it up,
they're accepting that they will die in
a few years.
When they actually could do something
about it. Whereas, the person who is
free from sensuality
has no interest in accepting that deal
because they see it as optional.
But, see, it's not that for the person
who has desire, it's now mandatory.
Uh
uh difficult doesn't mean mandatory.
Difficult to overcome doesn't mean
mandatory. So, it's just because of not realizing
So, it's just because of not realizing
like, wait, I actually have an option
not to die in a few years and I'm
choosing to forsake it.
That you would
uh not think just not thinking about it,
not reflecting on it,
you would just continue living as
normal.
So, it's that it's that um
again, even when everything is perfectly
fine, the fact that you delight in sensual
the fact that you delight in sensual
pleasure
has this huge weight behind it
because you may not get it.
Even when after you got it, you may not
get enough of it.
Uh while you're having it, other people
might uh compromise it.
Um
it may,
you know,
it are just so many variables
that are between you
and that pleasure
that it's only by ignoring that entire
scope of
tribulation that come with it that you
would think oh yeah this is actually
worth it.
>> So a modern simile actually for the
whole charcoal pit leper
story would be a drug addict because we
don't have this these days anymore. You
know we most people probably don't even
know what leprosy is.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and we probably don't have any
disease that comes close to it in terms
of as well the treatment
you know having this kind of super
painful treatment
maybe cancer and that kind of these kind
of cocktails that you get.
>> not it's it's there's no like impulsive
behavior you know.
>> Yeah.
>> But yeah the drug would because the drug
is like
you really you do it only because you
it's very painful not to.
>> And if you're free from that addiction
you would never go back
>> Mhm.
>> to like
>> Yeah.
>> taking the drug or going to
>> that the immense contrast
between being free from it and and
being free from it and and
having the addiction like you couldn't
like once you're out of the hole
where not doing it is very unpleasant
not doing it is very unpleasant
which is basically what distorts your
perspective. It biases you
It biases you
cuz it's just a natural human bias that
things that are inconvenient or
difficult you want to write them off as not
you want to write them off as not
necessary.
So
if that bias was gone for whatever
reason in the case of sensuality it would have
in the case of sensuality it would have
to be that you overcame the desire
but even with the drug, like let's say
you just
magically were
something happened that just made you
not an addict anymore. Actually had the
option not to give in to the drug.
Um
it would be clear to you like how
you were like the entire
uh
doom trajectory towards doom that you're
trajectory towards doom that you're
bringing yourself to. Yes,
for a certain gratification, but
that part of including the danger
including it, basically, it that is what
frees you from the desire.
You don't have to deny the
gratification. You have to
realize that the the gratifi- the danger
is already greater.
As the Buddha would say, the sensual
pleasures are
uh
they're painful. They're
much uh
uh
provide much despair.
And the peril there is what is greater.
>> And in in the sense of
maybe where the actually the addiction
analogy's much better says well that to
overcome an addiction you need to change
your whole way of life. You might need
to move, change the district, change
your friends, change the people you
associate with because everything was
based on that addiction
that you get the stuff, that you have
easy access to it.
Um
whereas I think for a leper, I'm not
sure how that
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yes, it's it's
especially when
when
the Yeah, the things that gain their
meaning or their significance to you because of
or their significance to you because of
the addiction.
You would only be implicitly
having a favorable attitude towards the
addiction by keeping them around.
So, yeah, certain friends, certain like
when the Buddha talked about bad
friendship. Um it's not like actively
Um it's not like actively
uh criminal
sort of very, very bad people under
every circumstances. It's just people
who have values that oppose the dhamma.
Which is anybody who
doesn't see a problem with sensuality.
So, um
um
you start reflecting on that danger for
yourself. Because you have to see it. Like you you
Because you have to see it. Like you you
can't be
operating again just based on um
religious zealotism. And you might go, "Yeah, the
zealotism. And you might go, "Yeah, the
Buddha said that it's bad." And even if
you actually believe in it and you have
faith in it and stuff. But the desire
will only fade
if you clearly for yourself see like
even if I was the last person in this
planet and nobody would judge me on
account of it,
the the the the charcoal pit doesn't go
away. For myself, like how my mind will be
For myself, like how my mind will be
afflicted
if I were to delight in this.
So, if you start cultivating that
if you start cultivating that
perception, actually
then naturally you will start inclining
away from certain environments and
certain people. But the thing is
uh
usually like you have to do it the other
way around because
you won't be able to develop the
perception of danger sufficiently or it
won't sink in sufficiently enough
because you're acting out.
Like because you're still actively
reinforcing the
the
priority of the gratification through
your actions.
You're still seeing that as as
um like training yourself.
You're seeing that as more fundamental.
So, there has to be a
uh an extent of forceful withdrawal.
Where even if the withdrawal symptoms of
the drug are still there,
you're still not consuming it.
So, you you can't expect that you will
like think and reflect and clarify and
then suddenly I won't feel like
consuming the drug and then I'll be
fine. You have to plan for a
You have to plan for a
usually a very great deal
of uh, resistance of like I I want to
take it, but I decided I won't.
So, you you
uh,
distance yourself from certain
environments, certain people
certain people
that for you
were engaged with
only for the sake of sensuality.
You start keeping the precepts
and whenever that desire comes up,
you reflect on the danger.
And you clarify it.
It doesn't matter if it feels harmless.
Like the thing is it it you're you're
not trying to
uh, figure out a theory cuz it's not a very
figure out a theory cuz it's not a very
complicated subject. It's not about a
uh, hidden kind of
uh,
you know, how the pieces come together
or something.
It's one fact, simple fact
that you just don't want to think about.
So, simply by thinking about it,
reminding yourself of it,
the same fact,
that's the work.
It's not to to deepen your the
complexity of your theory about the
danger of sensuality.
It's to not stop
uh, reminding yourself of that simple
fact. That the burn,
That the burn,
the pain of the desire,
how it simply feels in your mind,
is never
a sufficient like that always outweighs
the impact of any pleasure that you
could get
by acting while that burn is there.
>> So, rather than putting the pleasure
the gratification first
you put the danger first.
>> Mhm.
Yes, but you see the danger as a as
the burn that is already present.
It's not a
>> something
>> comes later.
>> Yeah.
>> It's not like like uh when the bad
things happen because then you could
you could theorize that oh well, if I
just handle all the variables well enough
handle all the variables well enough
uh I could hypothetically have
sensuality without danger.
But no, the simple delight
is the danger because of the burn that
it implies.
And and the burn and the uncertainty and
all of the
it puts you in this vulnerable position
basically. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> And that vulnerability in of itself is
painful. You would never choose it
You would never choose it
if you saw that that's worse than the or
that that outweighs the gratification.